Our next speaker is Eric Garrison.
He's going to be speaking on
concerted evolution and unorthodox
recombination of human sub-telomeres.
Thanks.
Yeah, thanks for the opportunity
to present this work.
This is mostly the work of
Andrea Guarracino and myself.
We've been joined recently
by a graduate student at St.
Jude, Angela Gamafi.
And the background to this is
the Human Pangenome Project.
So the second version of this, Human
Pangenome, HPRC version 2, HPRC
2, is comprised of a bunch of
nearly complete assemblies.
And you can see that in this NX
plot that basically shows us what
fraction of the assembly you cover
by contigs of a certain size.
And so this is, you know, most of
our chromosome ones are almost
completely assembled.
And you can kind of see as you
go that many of the genomes are
actually tracking the references here.
And so they're very, very high-quality substrate to think about the
evolution of complete
chromosomes in humans.
And back story that's important.
They've been coming up a lot at this
conference for the first time in
biology of genomes.
We have lots of discussion of
variation graphs and genome graphs.
I want to point out that these graph
models here where you have genomes
walking through nodes, which represent
sequence, these are effectively
equivalent to alignments
between the genomes.
And they're the same.
It's just a different
way of thinking of them.
Actually, in this talk, we'll be
looking a lot more at this particular
representation because it's more
scalable, more flexible, and it lets us
go after these questions
for the first time.
In the first version of the Human
Pangenome project, also this has been
discussed a number of times, but we built
these chromosomes independently.
And so we would take some collection
of contigs we think go to a
certain chromosome, put them together
in the pangenome graph builder or a
mini graph cactus, and we would
build a graph out of them.
So we get these isolated components.
But what we discovered by experimentation
was that if we put together
acrocentric chromosomes, we would
observe that they form a single
component.
And actually, the tightest part
of this component where they come
together, this is the pseudo homologous
region on the short arms of the
acrocentrics that's been discussed.
And that is the cause of recurrent
Robertsonian translocations in
humans.
So we needed to see this.
But technical reasons led
us to break them apart.
And so what we wanted to do in the
second iteration of the Pangenome
project was to put all of
these genomes together.
And to do that, we couldn't build
a single graph reliably because of
computational constraints,
reliability of just the process.
And so we turned to a concept
called the implicit data structure.
So here, the foundation of all this
is an implicit interval tree that
lets us query from a target range,
or any genome range, find ranges
of other things that overlap it.
And so we would typically
write that in a tree.
But this is very big and
heavy, and you don't have to.
You can simulate the tree just by
sorting the intervals and doing binary
search over them.
And so this implicit model is actually
the foundation of how we go and
look through the alignments
to then look at the graph.
And so we effectively simulate a
graph by building this many-way
alignment.
We use a tool called WFMASH,
which is a variant of MASHMAP that
actually gets base-level
alignments out of it.
And then we just compress and
index all of the path files, the
pairwise alignment files that come
out, effectively making a kind of
interval forest over all of them.
And let's answer the question at
every part of any genome in the entire
set, what other genomes align there?
And we can do, effectively,
liftover across the whole set.
And if we want, we can render an
actual graph out of it if needed.
So you get this by doing
an all-to-all alignment.
And that's a pretty gnarly thing.
So if you really did it exhaustively
on these genomes, it's 465 or
466 if you count GRCh38,
you have a two septillion
cell matrix, right?
And that is clearly intractable.
And in order to avoid the quadratic
pollution that this would imply,
this is, by the way, bane of Memphis
XAI, which is burning a bunch of
methane to make quadratic
deep learning models work,
you can exploit a number of things.
So one is that the whole genome
alignment, it's very sparse.
So you don't actually have to do
complete alignment of every cell.
You already know how to do that
because you can use miniMAP2.
But panmixia means that most of the
possible pairwise alignments are
redundant because most of the genomes
are kind of similar to each other.
That means we don't have to do all pairs.
We can do some subset of them.
And so the idea is that we look
at everything transitively.
This shows a random graph where
we have the components colored in
different colors and we have the
fraction of the edges that we combine
between the 500 nodes
here shown as this P.
So one-tenth of one percent,
we have a lot of components.
If we were to look from any genome
to every other one, we wouldn't
make connections.
But as we increase this, we
achieve a single component very
reliably at just a fraction
of the total alignment set.
And so that's what we did.
So we aligned about 11 and a half
percent of all the haplotype pairs
to each other.
It's hundreds of thousands of alignments.
Well, not hundreds of thousands of
alignments, but I think about 25,000.
This is hundreds of times the
critical threshold to make a single
component.
And so we're basically guaranteed
to kind of simulate the full graph
without having to build it.
And as a QC of this, we can query
across a reference and just ask, do
we see all the other genomes here?
And in this panmictic population,
where all the chromosomes are basically
homologous to each other, you
effectively hope that in every megabase
pair of every chromosome, you
see all the other genomes.
And that's true.
The notable exceptions being ribosomal
DNA, some centromere regions,
and the sex chromosomes, where
you expect different copying.
So that's good.
Suggest it worked.
And then we wanted to understand
what else we can see.
We wanted to build this single graph
so we could see, is there anything
else like the acrocentrics?
And this is a heat map that shows us
at every position, it's every 100
KB window in CHM13, how many other
chromosomes do we see in these
alignments?
Not just CHM13 itself, but we've
been able to label all of the HPRC
assemblies and we can see
which ones we see in that set.
And you'll notice that the acrocentrics
very clearly show up, so we'll
be able to have a positive control there.
You'll also see the pseudo-autosomal
region, although I believe it's
masked on the version of Y that
we're using, so it might be a little
confusing.
But the thing that's important for
this talk is that at the end of
almost all chromosomes,
you'll see this peak.
And if you zoom in on a few, you
see that it's not just a generic
thing.
And by the way, we're masking
and ignoring telomeres here.
So we're looking just at the
unique sequence of the chromosome.
It's actually not so unique in many
cases, shared between different
chromosomes.
This is the acrocentric arms, right?
This is chromosome 1, chromosome 4.
So there's a particular kind of
pattern that's unique to every one of
the chromosome ends, a
set of relationships.
And so then the next step
is to try to understand
first the scale of that,
and then how are the
relationships working out.
So this is an attempt to
understand how big these
putative pseudo-homologous regions are.
These are regions that look like they're
recombining between different non-
homologous chromosomes.
We do this by going to the bundle,
collection of every set of HPRC
assemblies and every chromosome, and
we walk in from the telomere until
we stop seeing other chromosomes
in the implicit graph.
And at that point, we're on
just the chromosome origin, and
effectively we're marking on
this plot where that happens.
And so you see that on XY acrocentric
short arms, we go over the
500 kb that we were
considering in this study.
Par 2 is in the 300 kb
range, so we confirm that.
But you'll notice that you have a
distribution of lengths in the tens
to hundreds of kb kilobase pairs across
almost all the chromosomes, with
a few exceptions.
One, two, three, four, five,
yeah, seven exceptions.
We note they don't seem to be
mixing like the other ones.
And so, of course, we're going to
build a graph to see this, and yeah,
so then we orbited this hairball
for a minute and decided we couldn't
understand anything that was
going on in here directly.
This is not as clear as the combination
of acrocentrics that we saw,
but it does make one
component, which is nice.
And to understand what's going on
inside of it, we're going to untangle
it in some sense.
We're going to take bundles of
the contigs from each one of the
chromosomes and then
compare them to each other.
And so we have this bundle, for
example, from chromosome 8q, and we can
compare it to chromosome 10q
within the space of this graph
by effectively thinking about the
overlap of those two bundles, like how
much of the overlap we use a Jaccard
metric, which is asking how many
base pairs on the intersection of
those two versus the union of them.
So that gives us this way of
looking at the interchromosomal
relationships that's actually pangenomic.
It's considering the whole set of genomes.
Yielding, and that yields this heat
map, actually, which is, we have
this kind of phylogenetic relationship,
which we're, this is just for
grouping.
We don't really know or think
directly that there is a phylogenetic
relationship between
the subtelomeric ends.
But you see that there is a very,
very distinct cladal structure.
It's not just one big blob.
There are groups of
things that fit together.
There are these sets.
This is the acrocentrics again, and so on.
And to give a little more definition
to this, we decided to use a
community assignment algorithm
that works on top of a graph.
In this case, the graph is actually
defined by the similarity metric
itself.
So there's weighted edges that say,
how similar are my two chromosome,
two subtelomeric PHRs to each other?
And the goal is to maximize the in-group similarity while minimizing the
out-of-group similarity.
And in doing this, we then result in
a set of 15 different communities
that describe the space here.
And you can see that there are still
inter-community relationships in
many cases, but we are kind of maximizing
the amount of inter-community
relationship.
What are some of these?
Just a little taste, because there's
41 of them, so it's very hard to
look at all of them.
On 4q and 10q, there are these
really large repeats of Dux4.
This is known as a relationship
with cancer and oncological
development.
And you can see these repeats here.
There's these tubulin genes
that are at the end of 10p
and 18p.
See this repeat structure there,
but only one on the other.
And there's a lot of olfactory
receptor genes, actually, and a lot of
pseudogenes as well in these regions.
And I'd like to talk a little bit
more about the gene enrichment, but
I think that work is
actually still ongoing.
What you see is that there does appear
to be an enrichment for cellular
sensory kind of things and
olfactory receptor genes.
So what's going on?
Why is this phenomenon very ubiquitous?
It must be maintained somehow.
I think it's important to consider
what's happening during meiosis and
when recombination actually occurs.
So you have this bouquet stage
in zygotene, when all the
telomeres are clustered or close
together on the nuclear envelope.
The telomeres are actually on
this manifold during meiosis.
And this is in maize, so it's not human.
These are the telomeres,
centromeres, and DNA.
This is another view of
it, the zygotene here.
The telomeres are labeled in red, a
little hard to see, because I guess
they're overlapping the green.
This is the cohesin structure
that's being labeled.
And then this bouquet, it dissolves
a bit in pachytene, but you still
have this anchoring on the nuclear
envelope during recombination.
So you have the opportunity for
recombination here, because you're
proximal, you're forced to be on
this manifold, and the sequences are
homologous.
And because you're physically in a
similar place, there's the opportunity
for common function to be
maintained and developed.
And so then we thought we'd make this
a little more quantitative in the
sense of actual 3D organization of
the cell, and so we went to Hi-C
data.
This is kind of crazy.
It's like a repetition of the whole
project just on mouse in order to
see this.
So we built the PHRs from scratch,
and then we're looking at
the Jaccard similarity.
So it's a metric of sequence similarity
versus physical distance implied
by the contact rate.
And you can see that there is
this quite strong correlation.
Once you get above zero similarity,
when you start to share,
then you see this kind of trend.
And also that this is amplified
in the bouquet stage.
So it makes perfect sense.
So it's in mouse.
But then we also did it
in human, of course.
So here we have effectively
observing the same thing.
This is with Pore-C.
So it's kind of multi-fragment
Hi-C and maps very well to these
regions.
And we also have the same thing
in regular Hi-C on CHM13.
And this does also match
our community assignment.
So we see some structure that matches
the communities we've assigned.
And you can, I think, appreciate
that inside of these communities you
have a slightly stronger rate
of contact than outside of it.
And so finally, just to close,
we did attempt to see if
we could catch this in the act.
And by looking at a multi-generational pedigree from WashU,
this plot is showing us
effectively untangling.
So we built a graph of
a child and actually
their mother's haplotypes.
And in the maternal haplotype,
we're asking, which one of
the mother's haplotypes are we seeing?
So we're effectively trying
to measure recombination.
And so you have haplotype 1
and haplotype 2 of the mother.
And this is showing how would I
reconstruct the haplotypes of the child
relative to those of the mother.
That's effectively what's going on.
So many of them, there's no recombinant.
You just have a single chunk.
But we see some kind of tantalizing
signals, like, for example, here,
which I'll zoom in on,
that where you have what looks like
ongoing gene conversion between
9p and 3p.
And this matches also the
community patterns we see.
So we think this is some
positive evidence for this.
But I wouldn't say it's conclusive,
because unfortunately, when you look
at much worse quality assemblies,
you see a lot more of this.
So it is compatible, but maybe
not definitive proof of an actual
recombination event.
But it would make a lot of sense,
I think, that you have many gene
conversion events in regions that
are physically close to each other
during recombination.
And so in conclusion, there
are pseudo-homologous
sub-telomeric regions that are the
near ubiquitous feature of human sub-
telomeres.
For lack of time, I didn't talk about
the backstory behind this, but we
have a lot of evidence over the years,
starting in the early 2000s and
with cytogenetics, that this is a thing.
But this is the first opportunity we
had to systematically observe it at
a population scale.
In humans.
And they cover around 3.5 megabase
pairs, excluding the acrocentrics
and the PARs on X and Y.
And so this is not an insignificant
part of the human genome.
We see that sequence homology mirrors
physical proximity in a nuclear
organization, which I think
is really fascinating.
And I wonder why, actually.
It's a chicken or egg question.
Is it that the sequence homology
is actually driving the physical
proximity, or is it the homology
just a result of the fact that the
proximity is there?
And as you just saw, a completely
assembled human pedigree suggests that
there may be ongoing and frequent
recombination exchange in these regions.
So with that, I'd like to
thank my collaborators on this.
I mentioned Andrea and Angela.
Heather Mefford, who's Angela's advisor,
actually has a wonderful review
on this from 2002, and we
replicated her results.
Although she just took a tiny slice
of the homology she had available.
I also want to thank Rob Williams,
Piotr Prins, and Vincenza Colonna at
UTHSC, and the Pangenomes Working
Group for generating and
understanding this data.
Thanks.
Okay, time for questions.
Thanks, Eric.
That was a really good talk.
I'm curious about your Hi-C analysis.
Hi-C is notoriously bad for
measuring interchromosomal
contacts.
And also, you know, really
bad at finding telomeric
contacts.
So I'm wondering how you are trying,
you know, how you're able to get
that signal.
So I admitted this.
We had to completely reanalyze all
these data sets because usually
they were excluding
mapping quality zero reads.
So we've done something that we
probably should try to correct for, but
we randomly assign the reads to
a location.
If they map exactly the same between
different locations, we randomly
assign them to one.
So that's the most principled
way of dealing with this.
The fact we can see it in Pore-C I
think should be reassuring because
you have many more fragments
together that help you to see it.
But that's a fact.
We couldn't see any of the signal
when we took the deposited data sets.
We had to realign them
in order to do this.
That was really awesome.
I have a question, if you can wax a
little poetic maybe, about whether
there's, whether you think possibly
that the sequence homology
actually maintains non-random
distribution of the chromosomes in
the zygotene, or if it's simply
the non-random positioning in the
zygotene that elevates the rate of
homology.
The chicken or egg question again.
It's not just zygotene.
We appear to see this consistently
at other stages of the cell cycle.
In mouse we had zygotene
meiotic Hi-C, in human no.
I wonder if transcription generates RNA
and an RNA can invade DNA and
that that generates a kind of,
I
guess a soup might be the right
word, but not exactly soup that
encourages the physical
proximity of these regions.
That might have some biological utility
because then things that have the
same function end up in the
same kind of part of the cell.
But that may be a story for another day.
If you look at this across all
segmental duplications, not just the sub-
telomeres and in response to Flores'
point, be a little more careful
about the control of the Hi-C data.
I have a question over here.
Let's take one more quick one.
I'm over here.
You showed some homology between
the P and the P and the Q and the Q.
Do you have any examples of homology
between a P arm and a Q arm?
Yeah, I do actually.
That's what I picked.
But I think we can find a few
instances quickly here.
What kind of implication do you
think that has because they're like
opposite orientations then?
I don't think that this cell really knows.
Frankly, the acrocentrics, yeah,
because they're kind of embedded in the
nucleolus.
For example, this is a
cluster you have P and Q
inside of it.
It is true, and we probably should
make a test to see if the Qs tend
to be closer to Qs and P's
tend to be closer to P's.
I think it's bound to something
actually because you tend to see the
stronger relationships between the
same arm, the shorter or longer one.
To me, it's a bit of a mystery
how that would be organized.
Okay, great.
Let's thank Eric.
Thank you.